Rockefeller Family Public Relations Department papers, Series 1-9 FA789A
Rockefeller Archive Center
- General - Foreign, 1947-1961; 5; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  - Venezuela - General, 1948-1961 (Box 47, Folder 448-449)
    Staff members in Venezuela; officials in Venezuelan government; political developments, changes in government, DR problems with AIA and IBEC in Venezuela.
  - Venezuela - Political Situation, 1950-1952 (Box 47, Folder 450)
    Correspondence with Bernardo Jofre in Caracas, Henry Bagley; information re. resignation of Ambassador Antonio Araujo.
  - Venezuela - Public Relations, 1948-1950 (Box 47, Folder 451)
    Basic Public Relations principles of AIA and affiliated organizations for Venezuela and VBEC; summary memo re. public relations in Venezuela; correspondence with Bernardo Jofre.
  - Romulo Betancourt, 1948-1949 (Box 47, Folder 452)
    Translation of "Neo-fascist militarism in the Hemisphere"; outlines for prospective articles to be published in American periodicals; translations of newspaper clippings on political situation in Venezuela.
- Politics, 1941-1960; 6; 1.9 Cubic Feet 5 letter document boxes
  - Arkansas, 1954-1960 (Box 47, Folder 453)
  - California, 1952-1958 (Box 47, Folder 454)
    Appeals from political organizations and candidates for contributions, most declined; LSR contribution to United Republican Finance Committee of LA county.
  - District of Columbia - National Republican Congressional Committee, 1950-1956 (Box 47, Folder 455)
    Contributions by family members.
  - District of Columbia - National Republican Senatorial Committee, 1944-1960 (Box 47, Folder 456)
  - Indiana - Senator W. E. Jenner - Capehart Inquiry, 1953 (Box 47, Folder 457)
    Inquiry info. contacts of IBEC and AIA with Export-Import Banks
  - Maryland, 1954-1958 (Box 47, Folder 458)
    NAR declines to speak at rally for Arthur W. Sherwood; recommendation that LSR not contribute to senatorial campaign for James Bruce
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller - General, 1956-1960 (Box 47, Folder 459)
    Press interest and speculation as to whether NAR will be candidate for Governor; offers to organize Citizens' Committee for NAR if candidate and form letters to be sent re. inquiries as to NAR's running for public office; groundwork for NAR campaign-TV appearances, form letters sent, designing campaign buttons, PR office at Rockefeller for Governor Headquarters; recommendations for positions on civil rights for new position paper.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Buttons, medallions and pins, 1958 (Box 47, Folder 460)
    Design of campaign buttons, Republican vote goal contest in New York; NAR letter to county chairman.
  - Family Contributions, 1940-1960 (Box 47, Folder 461)
    Records of political contributions, by individual and organization.
  - Memoranda Regarding Contributions, 1943-1961 (Box 47, Folder 462-463)
    1959-1961 and 1943-1958. Appeals for contributions to political organizations; contributions made.
  - Press and Radio Comments Regarding Contributions, 1952-1956 (Box 47, Folder 464)
  - New York City - General, 1941-1958 (Box 48, Folder 465)
    Family contributions to candidates campaign funds and general political organizations; on behalf letters.
  - New York City - Citizens Non-Partisan Committee, 1941-1953 (Box 48, Folder 466)
    Contributions made by family members; organization of Committee, DR form letter inviting membership.
  - New York City - Javits, Jacob, Eric, and Benjamin, 1950-1956 (Box 48, Folder 467)
    Contributions to Jacob Javits senatorial campaign, NAR form letters soliciting contributions for Jacob Javits campaign fund.
  - New York City - Mayoralty, 1949-1953 (Box 48, Folder 468)
    Riegelman, Isaacs, Carter, 1949-1953. Family contributions made, recommendations re. political contributions made to brothers by HNK; recommendations re. invitations to serve on committee.
  - New York City - National Republican Club, 1956 (Box 48, Folder 469)
    NAR contribution November 29, 1956; other appeals to family members declined.
  - New York City - Mayor Wagner-Committees, 1953-1957 (Box 48, Folder 470)
    DR members of Mayor's Advisory Council - Committee of Business and Finance. (Chrm. ); recommendation that LSR decline to serve on Special Committee on Technical Professional Manpower.
  - New York City - Women's National Republican Club, 1951-1960 (Box 48, Folder 471)
    Recommendations re. invitations and appeals.
  - New York City - 9th Assembly District, 1946-1960 (Box 48, Folder 472)
    Contributions to Republican Club by Mr. and Mrs. JDR, Jr., contributions by family members to Republican organization.
  - New York City - 17th Congressional District, 1950-1960 (Box 48, Folder 473)
    Family contributions to campaign funds for Congressman John Lindsay; appeals for contributions to campaign of Frederic R. Coudert, Jr. declined.
  - New York City - 18th Congressional District, 1946-1950 (Box 48, Folder 474)
    Contributions to Bryan, Ellis, Donovan campaigns.
  - New York City - 20th Congressional District, 1946-1954 (Box 48, Folder 475)
    Appeals declined; DR contribution to campaign fund for MacNeil Mitchell October 1946
  - New York City - 22nd Congressional District, 1946-1956 (Box 48, Folder 476)
    Contributions to Reynolds and Roque campaigns by NAR
  - New York State - General, 1942-1958 (Box 48, Folder 477)
    Contributions made by family members; noting analyses for Westchester County; memos on political situation in New York State; coordination of effort for NAR gubernatorial campaign
  - New York State - Government, 1951-1959 (Box 48, Folder 478)
    DR agrees to serve on Advisory Panel to Planning Commission Feb. 58; NAR agrees to serve as vice chairman for "Salute to Seasons"; NAR declines to serve on NYS-NYC Fiscal Relations Committee; recommendation re. DR approval on comments on Water Supply Report of Committee on City Affairs; invitations regretted for NAR; NYC anti-crime commission - recommendation that LSR and DR decline to serve
  - New York State - United Republican Finance Committee, 1944-1960 (Box 48, Folder 479)
    Contributions made by family members
  - New York State - New York Republican County Committee, 1947-1960 (Box 48, Folder 480)
  - New York State - New York Republican State Committee, 1942-1960 (Box 48, Folder 481)
    Contributions made by family members; recommendations on invitations to serve.
  - New York State - Re-election of Senator Ives, 1952-1954 (Box 49, Folder 482)
    NAR serves as chairman of Citizens Committee for the re-election of U.S. Senator Irving M. Ives; PR staff participation in publicity efforts; NAR contribution to Independent Citizens Committee for Ives.
  - New York State - Dinners for IKE, 1959-1960 (Box 49, Folder 483)
    LSR member of Committee for the Dinner with Ike; contributions to Republican Campaign Dinner by JDR, Jr., DR, LSR; "Thank you, Mr. President" contribution by NAR; remarks by Winthrop W. Aldrich at "Dinner with Ike" January 27, 1960.
  - New York State - Westchester Republican County Committee, 1946-1959 (Box 49, Folder 484)
    Contributions made by family members.
  - New York State - Westchester County - 27th Congressional District, 1956-1960 (Box 49, Folder 485)
    Appeals for contributions; NAR agrees to serve as elector September 1956; NAR contributions to Mt. Pleasant Republican Committee for Congressman Gwin
  - New York Young Republicans Club, 1946-1958 (Box 49, Folder 486)
  - Virginia - Virginia Democrats for Eisenhower, 1952 (Box 49, Folder 487)
    Appeals for contributions to campaign of Senator Harry F. Byrd of Virginia. DR, LSR gifts; WR contribution for Va. Democrats for Eisenhower.
  - Memoranda - General, 1946-1959 (Box 49, Folder 488)
    Candidates voting records; background on possible Presidential candidates; JEL recommendation re. family campaign contributions; recommendation that Winthrop W. Aldrich join Bi-partisan Citizens Committee for fair elections.
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower, 1956-1959 (Box 49, Folder 489)
    Political contributions made; NAR appearance on TODAY show January 13, 1956 to discuss forthcoming "Salute to Eisenhower" at Madison Square Garden January 20, 1956.
  - Citizens Committees for Eisenhower-Nixon, 1952-1958 (Box 49, Folder 490)
    Public Relations recommendations on family, giving to political committee.
  - National Citizens for Eisenhower Congressional Committee, 1954 (Box 49, Folder 491)
  - Eisenhower Presidential Election Program, 1952-1955 (Box 49, Folder 492)
    Translations of Latin American newspaper articles re. election of Eisenhower; summary of policy statements made up by Gen. Eisenhower; proposed Eisenhower anthology - no action indicated.
  - Eisenhower Platform Program Comparison and Memos, 1951-1952 (Box 49, Folder 493)
    Comparison of British Labor Party Election Manifesto 1951, Democratic Party Platform 1952 and Republican Party Platform, 1952; Planks of Republican and Democratic Party Platforms; Inter-American relations, 1948.
  - Youth for Eisenhower, 1951 (Box 49, Folder 494)
    Appeal for contributions to Youth for Eisenhower movement; interviews declined.
  - Fair Campaign Practices Committee, 1954-1959 (Box 49, Folder 495)
    Recommendation that the brothers not contribute, JDR, Jr. Contributions.
  - Samuel Lubell, 1956-1958 (Box 49, Folder 496)
    Study of attitudes of people in Los Angeles to the United Nations and UN agencies; proposed opinion reporting workshop, S. Lubell statement re. resolution for disarmament plan; "Sputnik and American Opinion, Vice President, Richard M. l\Tixon -' Latin. American Trip, 1958 Reports from IBEC staff members of attitudes and local press comment on Vice President's visit to Latin America and ensuing incidents.
  - Chat Patterson, 1949-1952 (Box 50, Folder 497)
    Appeal for campaign contribution for Congressional candidate from Ohio.
  - Vice President Nixon - Latin American Trip, 1958 (Box 50, Folder 498)
  - Republican Party - General, 1946-1949 (Box 50, Folder 499)
    Brothers memo re. election returns showing Republican control of Congress; NAR speech at Academy of Political Science, November 7, 1946; proposed Republican Open forums - contributions made; record of political telegrams sent; Brazilian Press reaction to VP Nixon visit, 1956; "The 1956 Plan"; political situation in New York State.
  - Republican Campaign, 1959-1960 (Box 50, Folder 500)
    Political situation; clippings on NAR
  - Republican Convention - San Francisco, 1956 (Box 50, Folder 501)
    NAR role in convention as alternate at large; summaries of recent news and comments at convention, Stassen - Nixon relations.
  - Republican Elephant Campaign Buttons, 1956 (Box 50, Folder 502)
    Drawings for elephant emblem; copyright and production information
  - Republican Growth Theme, 1952 (Box 50, Folder 503)
    U. S. growth theme from standpoint of appeal to mass audience; promotion ideas for individual parts of growth theme; economic themes and publicity strategy; speech material; comparison of party platforms.
  - H. E. Stassen for President, 1951-1952 (Box 50, Folder 504)
    Stassen Recent Political Profile; statement on efficiency in government and his proposed elimination of "loafers".
  - United States Government, 1951-1960 (Box 50, Folder 505)
    U.S. business relations in Latin America; State Department activities, JDR 3rd Japan interests Point 4. Public Relations advice 7 issues to NAR; DR, and JDR 3rd.
  - United States Government Arts Bill, 1954-1960 (Box 50, Folder 506)
    Proposed legislation for a federal arts program. Proposed changes in tariff law.
  - United States Government Foreign Cultural Relations Study, 1955 (Box 50, Folder 507)
    NAR requests FAJ, WH, JEL to outline possible study of international cultural relations. Outline prepared but no action. NAR acting for DDE
  - United States Government State Department, 1946-1947 (Box 50, Folder 508)
    Termination of Office of Inter-American Affairs (1946) NAR endorsement of Fair Employment Practice Act and foreign information program. NAR support of Institute of Inter-American Affairs.
  - Temporary State Commission on the Constitutional Convention, 1956-1957 (Box 50, Folder 509)
    Preparations for commission. Selection of staff. Public information program. NAR objectives.
  - News Summaries, 1956-1959 (Box 51, Folder 510-516)
- Family Members and Interests, 1946-1961; 7; 4.18 Cubic Feet 11 letter document boxes
  - Lucy T. Aldrich, 1954-1956 (Box 52, Folder 517)
    Biographical sketch including story of Capture by Chinese bandits in 1923; obituary (died January 12, 1955); memo re. preparation for including Atlantic Monthly article of November 1923 in the book of letters between AAR and LTA.
  - Mary B. French - "Thoughts and Meditations", 1954-1955 (Box 52, Folder 518)
    Publication arrangements made for memorial book of selections from Mrs.. French's notebooks preparation of manuscript; checking copyrights for some selections used. Manuscript was compiled and edited by Miss Anna Rice. Distribution of copies; certificate of registration with Library of Congress covering copyright
  - Elon Huntington Hooker (Mrs. JDR 3rd), 1956 (Box 52, Folder 519)
    Bio of Mrs.. Hooker's father Dexter Ferry; press release re. Mrs.. Hooker's death June 6, 1956.
  - Rockefeller Letter to Eisenhower, 1957 February 15 (Box 52, Folder 520)
    The News Deutschland (official communist party organ in East Germany) published an alleged secret letter to President Eisenhower from NAR written in January, 1956 in which he told Eisenhower how to get economic and military control of the
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - Marriage to Mrs. Martha Baird Allen, 1951 (Box 52, Folder 521)
    JDR, Jr. Marriage to Mrs.. Martha Baird Allen, newspaper clippings, press release.
  - Conservation Book - "The Heritage of Every American", 1956-1960 (Box 52, Folder 522)
    2 copies of editorial prospectus; text revisions, list of photos to be used, captions; the original title was "This is Our Land: The Picture Story of One Man's Efforts to make bur Natural Heritage More Rewarding to All".
  - Conservation Book - "The Heritage of Every American" - Background, 1956-1960 (Box 52, Folder 523)
    Background information; suggestions made concerning photographs, text, change of tile and introduction; book review from major newspapers; suggested distribution to newspapers, government officials and officers of related organizations; decision not to reissue the book in a lower cost edition.
  - Mrs. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - Memorial Booklet, 1948-1951 (Box 52, Folder 524)
    Obituary; press release made by Riverside Church; text of memorial service; arrangements for memorial booklets.
  - Mrs. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (Abby A. Rockefeller) - Death, 1948-1949 (Box 52, Folder 525)
    Copies of obituary; text of memorial service; AAR gifts to museums; copy of will July 2, 1947; MOMA resolution; statement re. preparation of Chase book about AAR; copy of Memorial Service booklet.
  - Abby R. Mauze Biography, 1959 (Box 52, Folder 526)
    Copies of December 1959 bio of Abby Rockefeller Mauze.
  - Mrs. Irving H. Pardee, 1949-1953 (Box 52, Folder 527)
    Bio of Dr. Pardee March 1949; obituary of Dr. Pardee April 10, 1949. Press release re. Abby R. Pardee marriage to Jean Mauze April 1953.
  - Mrs. George Dorr O'Neill (Abby O'Neill), 1949-1958 (Box 52, Folder 528)
    Engagement press release February 6, 1949; press release re marriage June 23, 1949; thank you note - Mrs. Irving Pardee re. scrapbook of press clippings re. Abby engagement;. press release - Mrs.. O'Neill becomes trustee of Bradford Junior College.
  - John D. Rockefeller, 3rd, 1947-1961 (Box 52, Folder 529)
    Proposed biographers of JDR Jr; press releases re. births; awards and honorary degrees; resignation from board of directors of New York Life Insurance Company; JDR 3rd interest and travel in Asia; press comment; recommendations and comments regarding JDR 3rd activities, including Lincoln Center, juvenile delinquency, Asian interests, "Personal program to strengthen democracy; 1953 memo recommending using tremendous unexploited potentialities of television to reach youth of the U.S.; objective and focus of JDR 3rd's Asian interest.
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Biographies, 1947-1966 (Box 52, Folder 530)
    Copies of biographies prepared; lists of interests and activities.
  - Mrs. John D. Rockefeller 3rd (Blanchette Hooker), 1951-1960 (Box 52, Folder 531)
    Time magazine article on Blanchette's modern art collection August 27, 1951;. declination re. becoming chairman of Women's Division of NYC. Olympic Committee; Public Relations biography October 1958.
  - International House - Japan, 1952-1953 (Box 53, Folder 532)
    Reports to JDR 3rd on the International Center and International House in Tokyo, political situation; ground-breaking ceremonies for IR-Japan December 1953.
  - American Youth Hostels, 1947-1959 (Box 53, Folder 533)
    Proposed European travel opportunities; for students; press release re. 15th anniversary of hostelling and re-election of JDR 3rd as president December 4, 1949; suggestions for AYH, annual reports and brochures; JDR 3rd reports and speeches.
  - Lincoln Center, 1956-1961 (Box 53, Folder 534-535)
    General correspondence; prepared statements; progress reports.
  - Lincoln Center - Pamphlets, 1956-1961 (Box 53, Folder 536)
    Printed material on Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts.
  - Lincoln Center - Plans and Financing, 1956-1957 (Box 53, Folder 537)
    Report on survey to determine feasibility of creating and operating a performing arts center in NYC by Day and Zimmermann, Inc. 1956; Lincoln Square slum clearance plan, 1956; Lincoln Center preliminary description, 1957.
  - National Urban League, 1949-1959 (Box 54, Folder 538)
    Family interest in and relationships with League
  - National Urban League - Rockefeller Art Exhibit, 1958-1959 (Box 54, Folder 539)
    Arrangements for "A Family Exhibit" for benefit of League
  - Policy and Planning Committee - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1954-1961 (Box 54, Folder 540)
    Agendas and status reports concerning JDR 3rd activities committee meetings
  - Nelson A.Rockefeller, 1957-1961 (Box 54, Folder 541)
    Memos on oil stock holding, automobiles, overseas travel, building for press appearances after 1958 election, use of land at Tarrytown.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Biographies, 1947-1959 (Box 54, Folder 542)
    Office prepared biographies for distribution.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Capital Hill Club, 1953-1955 (Box 54, Folder 543)
    Rockefeller family contributions to Club.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Farms, 1960 (Box 54, Folder 544)
    Move by Venezuelan Government to expropriate Palo Gordo farm. Details of negotiations.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Government Affairs Foundation, 1953-1957 (Box 54, Folder 545)
    Organization and financing of foundation. Political aspects. Reports.
  - James E. Hudson, 1955-1961 (Box 54, Folder 546)
    NAR political campaigns. Hudson's liquor license
  - International Development Advisory Board, 1950-1954 (Box 54, Folder 547)
    Relations between AIA and IDAB. NAR testimony before Foreign Affairs Committee. Distribution of "Partners in Progress".
  - Jewish Theological Seminary, 1950 (Box 54, Folder 548)
    NAR address and honorary degree November 21, 1950.
  - Museum of Modern Art (MOMA) - Betty Chamberlain, 1951-1953 (Box 55, Folder 549)
    Betty Chamberlain is head of Public Relations for MOMA; publicity problems, improvements which could be made, suggested ways to get publicity through museum activities.
  - Museum of Modern Art (MOMA) - Correspondence, 1951-1959 (Box 55, Folder 550)
    Museum activities, MR gifts to MOMA; LIFE article on Inca Art exhibition; summary of MOMA publicity September 1954-January 1955; MOMA fire; circulating exhibitions "Made in New York State".
  - Museum of Primitive Art (MOPA), 1954-1961 (Box 55, Folder 551)
    Formerly Museum of Indigenous Art. Charter application; press opening, Public Relations suggestions re. MOPA future; promotion ideas; publicity.
  - National Association for Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1956 (Box 55, Folder 552)
    NAR contribution to NAACP Legal Defense and Education Fund - appeal from Thurgood Marshall.
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1948-1961 (Box 55, Folder 553-554)
    NAR national chairman of 1949 brotherhood week. Preparation for activities. NAR participation. Speeches. Later requests for personal participation declined.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Trips - Brazil, 1946; 1952 (Box 55, Folder 555-556)
    Press coverage of trips.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller - Trips - Venezuela, 1951-1961 (Box 55, Folder 557-561)
  - United Jewish Appeal, 1946-1954 (Box 56, Folder 562)
    NAR chairman of 35,000,000 dollar drive for refugee Jews in Europe. Later contributions to annual drives.
  - United Negro College Fund, 1952-1959 (Box 56, Folder 563)
    Recommendations re. invitations to speak; NAR decl. to issue proclamation for Negro College Week.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller, Special Assistant to President Eisenhower, 1954-1956 (Box 56, Folder 564)
    Appointment. Office staff. Latin American press comment.
  - Nelson A. Rockefeller, Health Education and Welfare, 1953-1954 (Box 56, Folder 565-566)
    Office comments on HEW publications. NAR speeches.
  - Spanish Comic Books, 1949-1953 (Box 56, Folder 567)
    Consideration of comic books by John A. Brogan, Jr. to teach nutrition in Latin America. Negotiations. Use of Al Copp character in 10 experimental issues.
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - General NY Fund Campaign, 1949 (Box 56, Folder 568)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Population Council, Inc, 1953-1961 (Box 56, Folder 569)
    General correspondence. Reports of the Executive Officers. Press Releases.
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Products of Asia, 1952-1956 (Box 57, Folder 570)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - South East Asia Economic Study, 1955 (Box 57, Folder 571)
    United States Economic Policy - Asia, Report of the Special Committees on U.S. Economic Policy in Asia
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Mrs. O'Malley, 1950-1956 (Box 57, Folder 572)
  - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - House 242 East 52nd Street, New York City, 1949 (Box 57, Folder 573)
  - Winthrop Rockefeller - Biographies, 1955-1958 (Box 57, Folder 574)
  - Winthrop Rockefeller - Clippings, 1949-1959 (Box 57, Folder 575)
  - Winthrop Rockefeller - General Correspondence, 1949-1959 (Box 57, Folder 576)
  - Winthrop Rockefeller - Marriage to Barbara Sears, 1958 (Box 57, Folder 577)
  - Winthrop Rockefeller - Marriage to Jeanette Edris, 1956 (Box 57, Folder 578)
  - Winthrop Rockefeller - Mrs. Jeanette Edris Rockefeller, 1957-1958 (Box 57, Folder 579)
  - Winthrop Rockefeller - Press Releases - Divorce, 1953-1954 (Box 57, Folder 580)
  - Winthrop Rockefeller - Report on Veteran's Readjustment, 1946 (Box 57, Folder 581)
  - Winthrop Rockefeller - Winrock Farm, 1958-1960 (Box 57, Folder 582-583)
  - Winthrop Rockefeller - Citizens Committee on Educational Television, 1953 (Box 58, Folder 584)
    WR is chairman of committee to make reports favoring legislation for use of 10 channels for educational purposes; statement read before NYS Temporary Commission on the Use of Television for Educational Purposes.
  - Winthrop Rockefeller - New York University-Bellevue Medical Center, 1947-1958 (Box 58, Folder 585)
    Background material; fund raising campaign, WR contribution for appeal pamphlet; WR elected Chairman of Board of Trustees. preparation of press release; WR accepted a benefactor's award; WR statement re. Con Ed's gift of artificial kidney; dedication of medical science building.
  - Laurance S. Rockefeller - Caneel Bay Plantation, Virgin Island Park, 1953-1959 (Box 58, Folder 586)
    LSR purchase of Caneel Bay Plantations. Plans for national park. Mr. Stick of North Carolina, Criticisms of park policy.